Hello and welcome into the KE Report.
I'm your host Shad Marquitz, and today
we're getting an update on Mako Mining.
Mako Mining is traded on the TSXV under
the ticker MKO and on the Nasdaq under
the ticker MAKO.
And Akiba, it's great to get you back on
the show as always to do an update on
the operations not just from San Albino
but also from the Moss mine in Arizona,
and we will be getting into the updated
resource and the updated economics that
you put around the Moss mine. But
obviously a lot of interest still in
your development projects, so we will
briefly touch on the project in Nevada,
the Mount Hamilton project that you're
working on development, and then also
the project in Guyana at Eagle Mountain.
So, we will touch on all four projects
today, but let's kick it off with the
financials that you put out to the
marketplace on the 14th of August. Just
the high-level takeaways you want
investors to know.
>> Yeah, and thanks for having me on again,
Shad.
I mean, the the best takeaway from the
these earnings is that
we effectively have our smallest asset,
the San Albino mine, as our only fully
ramped up mine. We have a little bit of
contribution from the Moss mine that we
picked up that at a bankruptcy about a
year or so ago, but there's still a good
solid 6 or 7 months of de-bottlenecking
that we need to
to do over at Moss to to get it to the
level of the the economics that we put
out a month or so ago with the the
43-101 report due to be filed uh next
week. And then we have our our two
larger projects in development. So, when
you think about that as as context is
that if you actually do have two
relatively large development assets and
then one mine that's not being ramped
up, it does mean that there's
effectively like a drag on earnings from
those assets just because they're not
productive
or at least not at the level that they
they should be when they're fully ramped
up. So, all that's being said is that
even with that, our economics I think
are are extraordinary for a company of
our size.
I do use these metrics, which I think
are are used quite often for generalist
math, but is is very rarely seen in
mining, which are return on equity and
return on assets. And the reason why the
mining industry doesn't use it is
because there there ROE and ROA's have
been horrible over the course of the
last 20 or 30 years for obvious reasons.
It's because this has been an industry
that has approached both project
development and inorganic growth through
means of just getting bigger for bigger
sake. So on the project development
side, that kind of means you you buy an
exploration asset, you put hundreds of
millions of dollars of exploration
capital and potentially hundreds of
millions if not billions of dollars of
development capital to get it up and
running. And then lo and behold, you
have a fairly inefficient balance sheet.
And even if the mine winds up working at
the end of the day, you have this drag
on your balance sheet for all this
capital that you've spent beforehand.
And then likewise, if you're going
through an acquisition strategy and
like Mako is is effectively a
a roll-up and an acquisition-based
vehicle. But the normal way of going
through acquisitions is to just issue
stock to go and acquire other companies
and other assets to get big for for big
sake. So it's not a surprise that the
capital on the balance sheet winds up
getting
bulky, if you will, and the ability to
actually generate returns on those
levels of of capital are just not there.
We printed
a return
on equity of
just under 37%
and return on assets, which I think is
the more
impressive number in the middle of
mid-20% range.
These are numbers that are as good if
not higher than the hyperscalers that
are out there. So these are our numbers
that that Google would be printing, that
Microsoft would be would be printing as
good if not better than than those. To
kind of put it into context about what
the underlying earnings of our
properties are. And I keep going back to
this is that I think a lot of of mining
executives have been trained [snorts]
for odd reasons to always emphasize this
is what our production level is. This is
what our resource level is. The end of
the day you're a public company. You're
a public company and your responsibility
is to generate returns for shareholders.
And the way that we look at our our
balance sheet is such is that the
returns that we generate relative to the
capital that we put into this business
is on par not just with other mining
companies, but on par with some of the
most successful companies on the planet.
So I think the the numbers that we put
out today with all the context about
where we are in our growth cycle, I
think have been been extraordinary.
>> Yeah, Keith has some great comments
there and highlighting that return on
equity and return on assets is kind of a
mold breaker for the mining sector, but
you're right, you can compare yourself
just to general companies whether they
be tech stocks or healthcare stocks or
finance stocks. So a real business
making real money and real return on the
value that you put into the company
getting an investment return back. So
what a novel idea in the mining sector.
Well, let's still let's maybe dive into
some of the metrics that people are more
accustomed to. Do you want to go into
the revenues or the net income or or the
costs that you have, those kind of
metrics?
>> Sure. So so our two let's call it one
and one and a half mining assets of our
of our four four assets that we
currently have in the portfolio,
I would view San Albino as hitting a
solid eight for the quarter. So it
produced and sold just over 10,000 oz
for the quarter. We don't provide
guidance over at at San Albino, but from
an internal budgeting perspective it
exceeded kind of our estimates by
probably low low to mid single digit
percentage
rates. So everything kind of went
smoothly and and most of that
outperformance was really just through
positive grade reconciliation. So, we
always take an internal modeling
approaches that are that are fairly
conservative with respect to geology.
So, it did outperform, but
in many respects, the the outperformance
that we have for for internal budgets
are not not surprising.
So, I give it a solid A.
At Moss, I give a C- in terms of of
where it is in its economic potential
cycle, right? And it's not an unexpected
C- right? So, we put out effectively we
we're calling it a project update, but
it's it's the first time that this this
company has had a declaration of current
reserves within its its platform across
all four of our assets. We never had
reserves over at San Albino. We don't
have reserves over at Eagle Mountain. We
don't have reserves over at that Mount
Hamilton. So, this is the first time
that this company has had a reserve
declaration with an economic study that
was associated with it. So, before we go
through
and put out economics to the market on
our assets is that we do need to have a
very good understanding of the
underlying geology of our project. And
there's there's a lot of attributes for
that reserve that we put out over at
Moss. I encourage everybody to go read
the report that will go out likely
Wednesday, potentially Thursday of next
week
for all the details, but the CliffsNotes
version of this
is that
you effectively have two different types
of geology. One on the the western side
of Moss. We we're mining from a couple
of pits over there. That's part of this
breccia that has a disseminated and
relatively low-grade gold. And then the
stuff to the east side of of the Moss
mine is vein hosted, which tends to have
relatively It's not a not a high-grade
mine by by any stretch of the
imagination, but it has higher grade on
the east side.
Last year, there was a permitting
constraint for us to do any of the
pre-stripping work that we needed to do
to access the stuff on on the east. Uh
we got that permit about 5 months ago uh
thereabouts. So, we're we're well into
the 4 months ago. We're well into the
process of uh of pre-scripting the
eastern side, the east pit, which has
higher grade material. And we should
start accessing that in January of next
year.
Uh likewise,
the way that this Remember, we didn't
build this this mine. And there were
there were certainly a lot of choices
that were made by by previous operators
that we would not have made if we had
the opportunity to build this from
scratch the first time. And some of
those the choices that they made were
were obvious uh and we fixed those
before we actually started restarted
mining operations. And there's now stuff
that's starting to pop up and we kind of
need to to correct as well.
So, the in the broad scheme of things,
uh we put in that that feasibility study
equivalent in understanding that uh once
we debottleneck our operations, we'll
have the ability to move our crusher and
expand it to about 14,000 tons a day of
throughput. Right now, at 100% capacity,
our our current crushing operations can
handle about 8,500 short tons a day.
So, that feasibility study included
after about 3 years to be able to to
expand it to to this 14,000 ton uh net.
So, the crusher would be able to handle
more than that including the
availability levels. And that's kind of
where you see the economics of the the
MOS study going in from a step function
from the first 3 years of operation
to the fourth year of operation.
What we're starting to incorporate right
now is that there are ways of, which is
actually not in the feasibility study,
but there are ways of accelerating some
of that that throughput enhancement
through the acquisition of of additional
equipment without triggering a broader
uh permanent review. There'll be some
permanent reviews associated with it,
but it won't be like the full EIS that
we'll will to have in order to get this
uh sustainably to to 14,000 plus tons a
day in a few years time. So,
with that said, is that we're in the
process right now of procuring some of
that equipment, and then also in and
around that time frame, let's say Q1 of
next year, we'll have the ability to to
either you you can look at it as either
being able to expand our our operations
incrementally or to remove a lot of the
bottlenecks that we have and actually
just run our our operations really
effectively at nameplate capacity
instead of kind of this this fits and
starts because of a lot of these these
design choices that the previous
operators made. So, all of that is kind
of a long way of saying that right now,
for this year, it's like a C- minus
operation, elevated cash costs and
all-in sustaining costs associated with
it. And then starting next year, you're
going to start getting more robust
economics. And then when we're in a
sustainable situation where we're
producing these 14,000 tons a day of net
throughput, that's kind of where the
meat of the operation uh really lies.
Now, that being said, even though Moss
was in this this call C- minus ranking,
as you pointed out, is that this was a
an acquisition that we made for for $2
million net. We've now returned over US
$12 million
to the balance sheet since we we started
running this thing. And it kind of puts
it into perspective is that
even though Moss is kind of like an uh
time mine right now, we're going to get
incrementally better starting at the
beginning of next year, and then start
to become exceedingly uh profitable in a
few years time. Even with that, it was
just such a [snorts] high rate of return
on the acquisition, and it goes back to
kind of our our positioning in the in
the marketplace is that I'm not looking
at acquisitions to make certain metrics
that the mining investment community
likes to see look better, like our our
blended AISC or whatever people tend to
look at. I am strictly looking at ways
of generating returns on the capital
that I put out. And Moss was really one
of these unicorn type investments that
you can make where you had super high
returns on on capital knowing full well
that this is going to be a a very
long-lived asset that not only will will
generate returns on the capital that we
put in, but also puts the company into
position where it's going to have access
to different types of capital than it
ever did before.
>> Yeah, Akiba, as always when following
Mako Mining, it's always a little
complex, but it's always worth it. And
so, even though it's maybe a sea mine is
mine in your words right now, I think
you're getting an A+ return on your
investment for it. And it was a very
bizarre way to make an acquisition and
how it all played out, but I think you
had to pay it off like in the first
month or two after you acquired it even
while you were still just doing residual
leaching. It was paying for itself. So,
it's a very strange acquisition. All of
them have been, whether we're talking
about the Gold Source in Guyana kind of
uh surprised the marketplace when you
did that, but also the Matt Hamilton
acquisition was kind of a
non-traditional one where using your
partners with Sailfish and with Wexford
to assist, and all of these have built
up, as you say, a portfolio that a lot
of them don't have the normal metrics
that mining companies love to tout. It's
strange that Moss is the first one to
have, you know, the proven and probable
and have such a detailed uh inventory
where San Albino's been the workhorse
for years and has been surprising people
to the upside for every year we followed
it with you. So, maybe again talk about
the non-traditional approach. You were
kind of alluding to it in that last
answer, but the non-traditional approach
you take at Mako to make creative
acquisitions and not necessarily worry
about doing all the typical tropes that
you see in the mining industry.
>> Well, right. I mean, there was a lot of
question marks about why we weren't
going through the the normal process of
generating a reserve and feasibility
study at San Albino before we started uh
construction of it. There's a simple
answer to that. It's not like we're
we're cutting technical corners every
year. We we're exceedingly
detail-oriented when it comes to our our
technical understanding of our projects,
but it goes back to to what mining
investors think that they want. And I I
think they actually look at these
reserve reports and the these
feasibilities and and PAs and everything
that goes it just so you can actually
have a data point to make people more
comfortable in how they're underwriting
their own investments. It's like people
don't like
making investments based on real data.
They like making investments based on
these these simple heuristics that
people put out just because they've
trained themselves to think that way
because of how the industry has behaved
over the course of the last few decades.
Now, we don't mind going through the
process of going through the the
technical disclosure. I mean, it's it's
a good
good exercise in terms of what we did
over at Moss. We're going to be
repeating that almost identically to to
what we have over at Mount Hamilton. The
issue with with San Albino is that the
geology is is so complicated that in
order for us to put out a reserve and
feasibility study that would be
credible, we would have to do so much
work on that asset that by the time that
we were ready to put out a feasibility
and a reserve and economic study on San
Albino, we've already mined through it,
right? The um
so it's it's a it's a type of of of
asset where it it does not and actually
it's one of one of my biggest
frustrations about Meg as that as you
said our our workhorse or our work shark
if you will is such where it really is a
very difficult exercise to prove out a a
long life resource base. And that not
only is difficult for for investors to
underwrite, but it's also difficult to
manage the operations cuz it really is
you're you're effectively on a hamster
wheel. Uh now, we've been mining this uh
continuously now for a little over 6
years. We we're probably the the biggest
uh step change that we're going to have
over at San Albino in the near future is
that we we just started moving ground
for initial portal development to go
underground. Uh Uh we'll be complete and
have first uh supplementary uh
or a resource coming out uh from the
underground likely by early Q4 of next
year.
Which is intentionally behind schedule.
I think when we first started talking
about the underground, uh we were
expecting to to be as uh as early as
late this year. Uh we found more open
pit uh resource and it's just a lot
easier for for us to do that and we just
want to make sure that we got a lot of
the kinks out of the way on the
underground side of things.
But, San Albino, the reason why it
doesn't have a feasibility study is just
it's complicated to to put it together.
And then,
the way that this got built uh between
2000 and
2019 and 2021
is that it it was actually okay not to
be in a position where we needed to ask
for for money from the marketplace. We
financed the initial San Albino through
a rights offering uh that was backed up
by the controlling shareholder back in
2019. And then, in 2020, there was an
opportunity to raise equity capital
through the broader market just because
uh it was in the pandemic where where
everybody had the ability to raise
equity. I don't think it was anything
special on the Mako side of things. So,
we were opportunistic about capital this
company. And then, that was the last
time that this company raised equity
until until a little bit after we
announced the Mount Hamilton uh
acquisition and we we raised equity at
that point in time not because we needed
it. We raised equity at that point in
time cuz it helped buttress the balance
sheet to make sure that we we did not
need to have any operational delay
between the time that that Moss got
ramped up to Mount Hamilton got built to
Eagle Mountain getting in construction
where we had all the capital in in in
the world to do that without any
additional external financing sources
debt or and to make sure that we were in
a situation where we had a robust enough
balance sheet where we can honestly say
that that we did not need to have any
capital constraints to do all four
projects simultaneously.
>> Yeah, it's been a interesting journey to
say the least, Akiba, to follow along
with this and it breaks a lot of the
molds in the mining sector and that's
kind of why I like it. And I think with
San Albino, the one of the very first
things you did is you came in and you
sterilized part of the resource, which
is not a move most companies would make
and it's because you didn't have the
confidence in the prior resource and you
wanted to redo it yourself. And like you
say, your team has really dialed in how
to mine what is actually a pretty
difficult deposit to mine, but they've
really dialed in the process and you've
been mining it for years now, and I
think your balance sheet and your
operations reports and your earnings
reports that you do quarterly speak for
themselves with San Albino, and you're
still finding a lot of other material
there as far as expiration. There's
still a ton of expiration. You'll
probably be exploring there for decades.
But anything else you want to say about
San Albino and then we'll cycle through
some of the other projects.
>> here's the point. It's not like we
sterilized the the resource. We just
like took it down, and I I think this is
another interesting anecdote about the
industry is that we took a lot of
criticism for writing down that the the
resource from like the 900,000 oz that
it that existed when the previous
operators were operating this to the
270,000 oz that we had it initially
scoped out uh for our 2020 resource
update. Everybody was making fun of us
like blah blah blah. Look at that
resource.
The The end of the day is that this was
the first time that there was any
credible geological and technical
information that was out there in the
market. And it's a good time
to take a little bit of rewind for some
of those critics and and the people that
that were out there is that my view of
those critiques are is that and and the
way that I translate it is I don't want
good information. I want to be lied to
because that way I can write my
newsletters on the basis of information
that is out there even though it's fake.
Whereas if I have real information and
technical support behind it
that is something that I would prefer
not to have because then I can actually
generate a narrative around a story
that really was not true. And I think it
really is an indictment for a lot of
these analysts that are out there who
really are are in a mode just because of
how the industry has trained them to
think by actually wanting to be lied to
with with technical information and we
just we just never played that game. So,
we we took our criticisms as as the
company got built.
I think we get a lot less criticisms
these days. I find it somewhat humorous
that those same critics
choose to be quiet now as opposed to
admitting their make a culpa if you will
by acknowledging that they were just had
a faulty thought process years and years
and years ago.
But I think it is it's a it's a very
unhealthy attribute in in the
marketplace and now we're kind of on on
the other end of it where where our
stock is now performing. It's it really
is starting to to reflect what the value
of the underlying assets are
and then now we're going to get a bunch
of other criticisms which are oh my god,
look how much this stock is is rallied.
I can't believe the stock is so hot. So,
it's a completely different and
different narrative over here and for us
like the only thing that we can do is is
underwrite our business in the in the
most appropriate manner or possible. And
then kind of use a lot of our approaches
when it comes to to not only
product development, but also how to to
utilize sources and and structures
in order to for us to to kind of lower
our cost of capital
to do more and more of these and grow
the company accordingly.
>> Yeah, I just think it's an interesting
point you made that a lot of the
industry is obsessed with the resource
estimate, the PEA, the PFS, the
different steps along the way and a lot
of times the companies know full well
they're not going to be mining most of
the material in their resources or their
economic studies are more marketing
documents and they're way off course,
but then analysts and newsletter writers
run with those and your attitude was why
don't we just mine it and show you and
you have done that for years and I think
the results speak for themselves with
San Albino and again the expiration
upside there. You still have tons of
expiration upside and I didn't mean to
say necessarily sterilize it, but it's
just you took the resource down by three
quarters. Not a move most companies
would have tried right out of the gate,
but obviously you're still mining there
and you're still finding more gold
there. So, I think the evidence the
proof's in the pudding, as they say. And
then with Moss, again a non-traditional
acquisition an acquisition of an asset
that the prior operator had struggled
with and they had made some decisions
that as as far as how they laid out the
site and everything that you we've
talked about that before, but as far as
it going from a C- minus to an A plus,
what's going to happen over the next
year just to put a little more color on
the Moss mine?
>> Yeah, so you alluded to this is that a
lot of the decisions that the the
previous operators did
a [laughter] lot of crazy mistakes that
they made along the way, too. But like
the the one core decision that they it
made you you may be in a position to to
agree or disagree with them, but it
wasn't necessarily crazy
was that they wanted to avoid triggering
an an EIS through through the NEPA
process, right? In the United States,
especially under under different
administration where where those things
could potentially take 10 years to to
get done. So, they were a small mine and
they kind of wanted to avoid it having
those those trigger and then they'll go
through like an EA part of the the NEPA
process to to simplify things. In order
for them to do that, they they kind of
built Moss in two phases. The first one
was to do this kind of like pilot
operation where they they essentially
put the the foundations for the crusher
on on private land and then they did
this expansion case like
slight expansion case to 2018,
but they were effectively constricted in
in how much ground that they can they
can grow with all the the on-site
infrastructure that needed to be put
into place, not just the the crushing
plant, but also waste dumps and heap
leach pads and and everything without
triggering this to an EIS level. So,
they they basically built this thing
kind of on on this little postage stamp
and it really limited a lot of the
flexibility for how this mine was
developed. Crusher was built too small.
There's a lot of components of the
crusher that wasn't there. The energy
requirements were were not designed for
the long run. And then when they they
were starting to to mine this thing,
they were basically mining just to keep
the lights on and kind of support a lot
of their the issues with their balance
sheet instead of actually trying to to
run this thing like like a healthy mine.
So, one thing that happened, we would
not have acquired this if it didn't go
through bankruptcy. So, a lot of that
financial stuff needed to get wiped in
order to to kind of like restart the
clock on the balance sheet, if you will.
And then,
we needed an opportunity to to kind of
like see what what are the things that
we can do in the relatively short run
without also without us triggering any
IS.
And then then eventually getting to a
position where where this is going to
get big enough where where we're going
to need to have to go through that that
kind of potentially have to go through
that process as well. So, in the
interim, let's say over the course of
the next year or so, we're going to
start accessing the the higher grade
materials. So, instead of a 0.3 type
type gram
operations will be in the high point
threes. So, just as I just under 0.4,
which also sounds like a little bit low,
but for all of your listeners who are
really good at math,
>> [laughter]
>> 0.4 is like a like a a third higher than
0.3. So, that actually is a very very
substantive difference between between
the two. And then also,
in the interim without actually having
to go and and and trigger a movement
from our crusher from from private to to
public lands, we have the ability to
to creatively engineer some enhancements
to that with with additional crushing
sources. And then, a lot of the plant as
it was designed, there was just no
resilience built into it. So, everything
is
>> [laughter]
>> every component is directly related to
the next component. So, if something
happens in one part of the the overall
plant, whether it's at the the front end
and in the
primary crusher or the back end on on
the conveyance systems, if anything goes
down, it's like the entire plant goes
down.
It really was a head scratcher in terms
of some of the engineering designs. So,
a lot of things there where we're we're
going to start re-engineering the the
plant. We've already re-engineered, but
start implementing a lot of these design
changes to make the the plant more
resilient uh so it can actually
effectively operate on a continuous
basis at nameplate capacity. Uh that's
going to be a huge improvement to the
operations as well. And then eventually
we'll we'll have our our EIS approved.
Who who knows how long that's going to
going to take.
And [snorts] then at that point in time
we'll have the ability to potentially
move at least some components of our
crusher onto onto federal ground.
Potentially move a component of the
crusher to access some of the resource
that was uh was effectively uh
sterilized in terms of where they placed
the crusher in the first place. And then
we'll re-access some of that that that
ore. That will take some capital to do.
It's all laid out kind of in our our
feasibility study equivalent uh that we
put out. But that's going to be a more
longer-term objective. Uh we're we're
operating under the assumption with that
technical report it'll take about 3
years.
Hopefully we'll have an administration
that can we can do it a little bit
shorter than that, but it could very
well be a little bit longer than that.
But that's probably a good uh first good
guess in terms of how long uh this is
going to take for it to be sustainably
run at 14,000 uh short tons a day.
>> I appreciate you kind of looking into
the future there a couple years in the
process and the different steps along
the way and how you will keep expanding
at Moss. Obviously a lot of interest on
Nevada and with Mount Hamilton. So, this
is the next project in the queue for
development. Just give us a quick sneak
preview of like what the process is or
an update on how it will evolve from
development into construction into
production.
>> Yeah, so we're we're starting to hire
people and we we're starting to get
equipment over to site. Uh we're doing
some basic groundwork.
The interesting thing about uh Mount
Hamilton is that uh the plan of
operations with the the lead agency uh
managing it the US Forest Service. The
original plan of operations in in 2014
was was approved for it to go ahead uh
with an operation and then
there was a a subsequent amendment by
the the previous owners of this uh of
Waterton and the private equity fund out
in Canada.
They did an amendment in 2018. There's a
lot of like like small stuff, but like
the big uh the big design feature
associated with this was the original
plan of operation uh contemplated a an
ore chute to convey
ore from the top of the mountain down to
the the bottom where the the leach pads
and and ADR plans and and everything uh
everything else was located. Uh so, if
there's like one technical challenge
about Molybdenum, it's like how do you
get the the ore from the top to the
bottom? Maybe that's as simple as that.
Obviously, there's a lot lot more
technical challenges, but that's the big
one. So, they they designed this this
ore pass uh that would basically just
just be this little little water slide
that that takes the ore from from the
top down uh the bottom.
That was not a very well-thought-out
engineering design. And Waterton
recognized that. So, they they asked for
a plan of operations change
to do a overland conveyor system to get
the ore from the top to the bottom.
Now, in doing that, and I don't know if
the the reason for this was they didn't
want to poke the bear on the permitting
side or or they just went through the
path of least resistance.
But, in the placement of the conveyor
system, they left the location of the
primary crusher, which was halfway up
the mountain. So, the primary crusher
was up at the top. They had a conveyor
system and then they had the secondary
and tertiary crushers down below. And
then eventually, the heap leach pad all
in the the valley at the the bottom of
the the mountain.
The reason why they left the the crusher
up there was it happened to have been
designed to be placed right next to
where the historical adit was being uh
located for the original 2014 plan of
operations.
In doing that, because that the mountain
is is fairly steep, if you actually
design your conveyor system, there's
going to be elements of that conveyor
system that were was going to have an
incline in excess of 20°.
And then if you're going to be running
this mine for the long run, that's just
not a very well engineered conveyor
system. Things would go wrong. The
maintenance on it, the ability to to run
this thing at fairly high throughputs
and things like that. It was just it was
not going to going to work in the in the
long run. So we redesigned that over the
course of the last 6 months since we we
fully acquired the the asset to
basically change a little bit of where
the the conveyor location is going to
be.
And then kind of redesign the the
initial placement of our our primary
crusher
in a way that that keeps all of the the
incline of that conveyor to to no more
than 12° at any any point in the path of
how the the ore is getting conveyed down
to the bottom.
In doing that though, is that that
requires like a minor change of a plan
of operation with the the US Forest
Service. So the
I'm going back and forth about whether
this was a a tactical mistake on on my
end or not, but we were fully
transparent with the Forest Service. And
we also because we're like changing a
little bit of location of the conveyor
system, we don't want to like make a a
boneheaded mistake and then not do any
combination drilling in this new route
and location.
So even though we were we were fully
permitted to do a combination drilling
before on the original 2014 and
subsequent amended 2018 area, because
we're now announcing a minor change in
the conveyor location, we can't
physically start doing everything that
we need to do to start the meat of the
construction over at 900. It's like this
this Heisenberg uncertainty principle
with US based permitting is that you can
be both fully permitted and and not
permitted at the same time. And that's
kind of like where where we are right
now. Uh the Forest Service is is has
promised us a a very expedited review
period on this this very very minor
location change of this this conveyor
system. Hopefully, we'll get that by uh
by the first week of September. If that
happens, I think that everything is fine
with our schedule, but this has eaten
into some of our our buffer when it
comes to
scheduling. So, everybody that's there
is like chomping at the bit to to start
the the meat of the construction. We're
hiring people. We have offices now in in
Ely, pretty well established. We're
doing like our our road work repair and
and everything that needs to be done
beforehand. But, there's a lot of stuff
that we should have been doing three or
four weeks ago that we still are unable
to do. And then if this this slips past
to to September, there's going to be uh
there's going to be incremental delays
to the project because of that. So, I'm
I'm hopeful that it's not going to be
anything like major, but it is one of
those situations where I made this
comment before.
Like uh people always criticize us for
for being in a in a risky jurisdiction
like Nicaragua. Um the US has risks
associated with it, too. And sometimes
there are even higher levels of risk
associated with this. Like stuff like
this, we would this would be like a a
very simple conversation that we would
have the regulator over in Nicaragua,
and then we would be able to do this
without any delays. In the US, any minor
change, irrespective of what is being
said at the uh at the top of the
administration, causes delays like this.
And it can be it can be a frustrating
exercise.
>> Yeah, it is a little humorous to think
about how much flak you've gotten for
Nicaragua, but how much easier this
would be if it was in Nicaragua. And
that Nevada is the number one Fraser
Institute uh or the number one or two
every year, and it's not without risk.
And it's just because of the permitting.
But, what does that mean for the
timeline? Let's just say that the
timeline does happen and you get it in
September. What would the build look
like? Just for people to understand on
the other side of it, when do you start
producing?
>> You give me a thumbs up on our Well, the
combination program
like placement is is is is
is associated with a bunch of other
stuff, right? So, our 2026 work plan and
then this this modified plan of
operation in the Forest Service is is
determined that that everything needs to
be taken care of at the same time.
So, the second second we get a thumbs up
and an actual number for a reclamation
bond to post, meaning here's the capital
that likely won't be from our balance
sheet, it'll be from from a surety
provider, but as soon as that is placed
in bond, we'll take 14 months. And then
in our conversations, like we're we're
saying, "All right, maybe maybe 2 weeks
from now." I I'm a little bit suspect
that 2 weeks is going to be 2 weeks, but
literally from the time that that that
goes, you're 14 [snorts] months to to
first gold pour. There'll be like a
ramp-up period after after that first
gold pour, but the first gold pour 14
months after that.
In our previous public disclosure of
before we put out our MD&A today, uh we
were operating on the assumption that
first gold pour would happen in in early
Q4 of uh of of next year. If what the
Forest Service is saying is accurate,
then
no harm, no foul. That that is
maintained. Though we said early Q4 of
next year, knowing that there was
probably about 2 months of a of a buffer
that led up to that. That 2 months uh is
now basically expended at this point. We
probably still have a couple of weeks
left in that buffer, but it's it's it's
nearly fully expe- expended at this
point.
>> Okay, so you chewed up a little of the
buffer, but you could still make the Q4
of next year. Worst-case scenario, maybe
it's first quarter of of the of the year
thereafter, but that just gets people
>> That would imply like another 3 months.
I will literally
I'll blow a gasket.
>> You'll pull out your hair if that
happens. Well, just to get people the
proper expectations cuz mining's not
easy and and and it's not easy to to
always keep everything on a perfect
timeline, but it sounds like at least
you worked in enough buffer to where you
still could probably make the Q4. So,
we'll keep tabs on it, and we'll keep
checking with how things are going at
Mount Hamilton. Just a real quick
comment on Eagle Mountain, too. This is
a even a bigger development project in
Guyana. Just anything you want to say as
far as the next steps there.
>> Yeah,
uh mineral agreement has been signed off
by the the cabinet. I think Steve and I
are trying to schedule a meeting to get
down to Georgetown to sign the thing.
And then all the public commentary about
the the ESIA is is in the process of
getting incorporated into
our [snorts] amended or like our final
ESIA for for approval. So, that's still
on track for let's call it Q3 this year.
And then hopefully we'll be in a
position to to get that approved. And
then get this thing fully permitted Q1
of next year. And then as soon as we
have the human resources available like
pulling them off of of Mount Hamilton,
then we'll start the real construction.
Some construction is actually already
starting over in in Guyana where to make
some improvements to to various bridges
and and crossings when we start carrying
over some some heavier equipment. But
like the meat of the construction will
will likely be in a position to start
let's call it late Q2 of of next year
thereabouts. And that should be about a
12-month schedule to get that that up
and running.
>> Okay, that goes around the horn. We've
touched on all four projects, kind of
the development and progression of each
one. All of them are works in progress.
All of them are moving forward. The
company is really transformed over the
last few years by adding these assets in
and then moving them in. You've got 1.5
mines in production and eventually Mazo
will be a full bore thing by about
another year or so. So, you'll see the
step change there and then Mount
Hamilton coming in right after that and
then Eagle Mountain coming in right
after that. So, there's going to be a
sequence of these mines turning on over
the next few years, which is going to be
exciting to watch. And we didn't even
get into all the exploration upside at
all these projects in this call. And
Akiba, I'll still keep throwing this
idea out there. Maybe we can jump on a
call sometime and just give people a
nice video presentation on all the
exploration upside and maybe we can fit
that in sometime in the not too distant
future. But lots of news on tap from
Mako Mining. And for those of you
listening in, if you want to follow
along with the news, definitely click on
the link below in the show notes. It
takes you right over to the Mako Mining
website, straight to their news section.
You can sign up for updates that hit
your email inbox or just follow along
with all the news as it drops. And
Akiba, as always, looking forward to our
next conversation.
>> All right, great. No, I appreciate it,
Chad.